A Guide to the Papers of Dorothy Allen Smith Berkeley and Edmund Berkeley, 1960-1994
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Dorothy Allen Smith Berkeley and Edmund Berkeley 1960-1994
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2764-d
This collection consists of ca. 3000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Edmund Berkeley, Jr., June 1999.
Biographical Information
After marrying in 1936, Dr. and Mrs. Berkeley lived in many college and university communities including Chapel Hill, North Carolina; Sewanee, Tennessee; Greensboro, North Carolina; Chestertown, Maryland; and Lynchburg, Lexington, and Charlottesville, Virginia, as Dr. Berkeley taught biology and botany in colleges and universities. The Berkeleys shared a long and productive scholarly career as biographers, co-authoring nine books and numerous articles, chiefly in the field of history of science. Their first book, John Clayton, Pioneer of American Botany was published in 1963; the most recent, The Correspondence of John Bartram 1734-1777 appeared in 1992. Other works included biographies of botanists-naturalists Alexander Garden, the Reverend John Clayton, the Reverend Mosely Ashley Curtis, George William Featherstonhaugh, and Dr. John Mitchell. They also published a biography of John James Beckley, friend and supporter of Thomas Jefferson, who was the first clerk of the United States House of Representatives and the first Librarian of Congress.
Scope and Content
This collection of ca. 3,000 items, 1960-1994, constitutes primarily the research correspondence files maintained by Edmund Berkeley (1912-1993) and Dorothy Allen (Smith) Berkeley (1911-1994) as they researched and wrote nine books, chiefly biographies, in the field of history of science. To these files have been added some family correspondence, photographs, and memorabilia.
Their research files were organized by state and research institutions; subject files were added as were occasional folders for individuals. There is a good deal of material from their research on the life of William Gibson, including a book manuscript that remains unpublished. They prepared a file of offprints of the artiles that they published. There is a quantity of photographic and other material either considered or used as illustrations for one or another of their books.
To these professional papers have been added some of their folders on family members and friends and some on subjects and activities. There is a very small quantity of family correspondence including letters from their children and grandchildren. They kept little of the family correspondence that they received, and routine Christmas and birthday cards have been destroyed. There are some letters written by DAB to EB when the latter was stationed in Puerto Rico during World War II, and a few letters that he received from his father. There are two albums of photographs taken at their Charlottesville home, primarily in the gardens, from the construction of that house in 1972 until about 1990. Additionally, there is miscellaneous material such as diplomas, certificates, passports, and the like, and some family photographs.
Contents List
- Series I: Professional and Working Papers
  - Academy of Natural Sciences (Box 1)
  - Alabama, University of, Press (Box 1)
  - Alabama (Box 1)
  - American Philosophical Society (Box 1)
    Grant, 1966; Meetings, 1971 & 1991.
  - Argyle, Duke of (Box 1)
    Argyll's Gardens
  - Armstrong, Alan W. (Box 1)
  - Articles, Possible (Box 1)
  - Australia (Box 1)
  - Bartram Biography, 1978- (Box 1)
  - Bartram, John (Box 1)
    Offprint from Bartonia Special Issue (1931) of articles by John Hendley Barnhart.
  - Bartram Association (Box 1)
  - Bartram, William (Box 1)
  - Bartram Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - [Bartram] Illustrations (Box 1)
  - Bartram, Royals (Box 1)
  - Beckley, John (Box 1)
  - Bell, Whit [Whitfield J. Bell, Jr.] (Box 1)
  - Berkeley Biographer [S. T. Buczaki, who worked on Miles Joseph Berkeley] (Box 1)
  - Boyd, Julian (Box 1)
  - British Library (Box 1)
  - California (Box 1)
  - Canada (Box 1)
  - Cambridge (Box 1)
  - College of Physicians of Philadelphia (Box 1)
  - Colorado (Box 1)
  - Connecticut (Box 1)
  - Cosh, Mary (Box 1)
  - Denmark (Box 1)
  - Dictionary of American Literary Biography (Box 1)
  - District of Columbia (Box 1)
  - Duke [University] (Box 1)
  - Early Southern Botanists (Box 1)
  - England (Box 1)
  - Ewan [Joseph], 1980- (Box 1)
  - Ewan Reprints (Box 1)
  - Featherstonehaugh [George William] (Box 1)
  - Florida [University Press of] (Box 1)
  - France (Box 1)
  - Geological Society of America (Box 1)
  - Georgia (Box 1)
  - Germany (Box 1)
    re publication of Moses Ashley Curtis biography
  - Gibson, William (Box 1)
    College of Physicians and Surgeons (W. B. McDaniel [and W. B. McDaniel]); Letocha, Charles [E.]; Maryland State Archives; Pennsylvania, University of; Portraits; [Research materials]; Princeton; Gibson Biography, Drafts.
  - Gift Copies Bartram (Box 2)
  - Gift Copies GWH [George William Featherstonehaugh] (Box 2)
  - Griffel, [Maurice] (Box 2)
  - Harvard (Box 2)
  - Historical Society of Pennsylvania (Box 2)
  - Historical Mss. [Manuscripts] Commission (Box 2)
  - History of Science (Box 2)
  - Holland (Box 2)
  - Hunt [Botanical] Library, Carnegie Tech (Box 2)
  - Huntington Library (Box 2)
  - Illinois (Box 2)
  - Indexing (Box 2)
  - Indiana (Box 2)
  - Ireland (Box 2)
  - Kansas (Box 2)
  - Kentucky (Box 2)
  - Leighton, Ann (Box 2)
  - Librarians (Box 2)
  - Libraries (Box 2)
  - Library Company of Philadelphia (Box 2)
  - Linnean Society, London (Box 2)
  - Louisiana (Box 2)
  - McKinley, Dan (Box 2)
  - Maine (Box 2)
  - Maryland (Box 2)
  - Massachusetts (Box 2)
  - Massachusetts Historical Society (Box 2)
  - Minnesota (Box 2)
  - Michigan (Box 2)
  - Missouri (Box 2)
  - Mississippi (Box 2)
  - Mitchell [John], Talk Reprints (Box 2)
  - Montana (Box 2)
  - Murray, Hon. Charles Augustus (Box 2)
  - National Archives (Box 2)
  - Natural History Museum (Box 2)
  - Nebraska (Box 2)
  - Nevada (Box 2)
  - New Hampshire (Box 2)
  - New Jersey (Box 2)
  - New York City, 1980- (Box 2)
  - New York (Box 2)
  - New Zealand (Box 2)
  - North Carolina, 1980- (Box 2)
  - Northern Illinois (Box 2)
  - Norway (Box 2)
  - Ohio (Box 2)
  - Oregon (Box 2)
  - Oxford (Box 2)
  - Palmer, Ralph (Box 2)
  - Philadelphia to 1980 (Box 2)
  - Permissions, Bartram [1979] (Box 2)
  - Permissions 1990 Bartram Corres[pondence] (Box 2)
  - Permissions, GWF [George William Featherstonehaugh] (Box 2)
  - Permissions (Box 2)
  - Periodicals (Box 2)
  - Philadelphia Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Publications, Our (Box 2)
  - Readers' Reports (Box 2)
  - Reprints (Box 2)
    E.B. & D.B.; Miscellaneous.
  - Research [Beckley] (Box 2)
  - Reviews (Box 2)
    Bartam, Beckley, Clayton, Curtis, Featherstonehaugh, Garden, Miscellaneous, Mitchell, Our.
  - "Three John Claytons," Paper 1965 (Box 2)
  - Phode Island (Box 2)
  - Royal Society of Arts (Box 2)
  - Royal Society (Box 2)
  - Runge, Bill [William H.] (Box 2)
  - Scotland (Box 3)
  - Smithsonian Institution (Box 3)
  - South Carolina (Box 3)
  - Sweden (Box 3)
  - Tennessee (Box 3)
  - Texas (Box 3)
  - UNC [University of North Carolina] Press (Box 3)
  - Utah (Box 3)
  - Vermont (Box 3)
  - Virginia (Box 3)
  - Virginia Historical Society (Box 3)
  - Va Mag [Virginia Magazine of History and Biography] Article (Box 3)
  - Virginia State Library and Virginia Cavalcade (Box 3)
  - Waterton, Charles (Box 3)
  - West Virginia (Box 3)
  - White, George W. Correspondence (Box 3)
  - William and Mary (Box 3)
  - William and Mary Quarterly (Box 3)
  - Williamsburg, Colonial (Box 3)
  - Wisconsin (Box 3)
  - Yale (Box 3)
- Series II: Offprints
  - "'The Ablest Clerk in the U.S.' John James Beckley" for the Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, 1962 (Box 3)
  - "'Another Account of Virginia' By the Reverend John Clayton," in the Virginia Magazine, 1968 (Box 3)
  - "Benjamin Franklin and a 'Dear ould friend'" in the Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, 1993 (Box 3)
  - "The First Librarian of Congress John Beckley" in the Quarterly Journal of the Library of Congress, 1975 (Box 3)
  - "The History of the Naming of the Lobolly Bay" in the Journal of the History of Biology, 1968 (Box 3)
  - "Dr. John Mitchell: The First Virginia-Born Scientist," 1971 (Box 3)
    Given as a lecture in 1971 at Mary Washington College, and published in the Occasional Papers of the E. Lee Trinkle Library.
  - "John Mitchel''s Plant Genera from Virginia" in Jeffersonia: A Newsletter of Virginia Botany (Box 3)
  - "Man and the Great Dismal" in the Virginia Journal of Science, 1976 (Box 3)
  - "Richmod's Three-Time Mayor" in Virginia Cavalcade, 1975 (Box 3)
  - "The Manner of Living of the North Carolinians" in the North Carolina Historical Review, 1964 (Box 3)
  - "Morphological Studies in the Celastracae" in the Journal of the Elisha Mitchell Scientific Society, 1953 (Box 3)
  - "The Most Common Bush or Vilest Weed: Some Unpublished Letters of James Petiver to William Byrd II" in the Virginia Magazine, 1987 (Box 3)
  - "'The Piece Left Behind'; Monroe's Authorship of a Political Pamphlet Revealed" in the Virginia Magazine, 1967 (Box 3)
  - "Spindle Development and Behavior in the Giant Amoeba" in Biological Bulletin, 1948 (Box 3)
- Series III: Personal Papers
  - Anniversary [50th] Dinner (Box 3)
  - Applegate (Box 3)
  - Art [Arthur Murray Whitehill, Jr., brother-in-law] (Box 3)
  - Barn Elms Bed (Box 3)
  - Berkeley, Edmund, Obituary (Box 3)
  - Bunny and Cynthia [T. Walley Williams and Cynthia Berkeley Williams] (Box 3)
  - Clippings and Cartoons (Box 3)
    Articles about DAB and EB, etc.
  - Christmas Cards to Mother [DAB] 1994 (Box 3)
  - Daniels, Jonathan, Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Frank [Francis Lewis Berkeley, Jr.] (Box 3)
  - Garden Diary, Dad's [EB] (Box 3)
  - Hunting Horn, Photographs (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Navy File [of EB] (Box 3)
  - Piedmont Virginia Community College (Box 3)
  - Resume, E.B. (Box 3)
  - Rose, Turner (Box 3)
  - Saint Paul's College (Box 3)
  - Spreen (Box 3)
  - Squam [Lake, N.H.] (Box 3)
  - Student letters [to EB] (Box 3)
  - UNCG [University of North Carolina Greensboro], Resignation (Box 3)
  - University League (Box 3)
  - Berkeley, Edmund and Dorothy (Box 4)
    Folder contains a miscellany of diplomas, certificates, passports, clippings, etc.
  - Sympathy Notes, etc., re Dad [EB], 1993 (Box 4)
  - Sympathy Cards, Mother's [DAB] death, 1994 (Box 4)
  - EB, Jr. to EB, 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - Letters to EB from his father, siblings, and DAB 1930-1944 (Box 4)
  - Lynchburg House, Papers re (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1935-1937 (Box 4)
    Kept by DAB re her wedding honeymoon, friends, relatives, etc. Some later photographs laid in.
  - "Bridal Chimes," (Box 4)
    A commercial volume for brides in which DAB listed wedding presents and clippings about her engagement, etc.
  - Folder of family photographs (Box 4)
  - Photograph album, 1972-1980 (Box 4)
    Containing photographs taken during the construction of EB and DAB's home at 142 Canterbury Road, Belair, Charlottesville, and of the gardens around that house as they were developed over the years.
  - Photograph album, 1981-, Continuation of the garden development photographs. (Box 4)
  - Photographs and other illustrations (Box 5)
    Considered by the Berkeleys for use in their books on John Clayton, John Beckley, John Bartram, John Mitchell, and Alexander Garden.